ah this is going to be controversial
what's up guys my name is CH welcome
back to my C++ series it's been forever
since the last episode but we're back
today we're going to be talking about
conversion operators in C++ plus simply
conversion operators just allow you to
convert from one type to another it
seems super simple it seems super useful
and to be honest in a lot of cases it is
but much like a lot of other C++
features it can definitely be abused
what I'm going to show you here today is
some really simple examples of how you
can use these to clean up your code
effectively and to make things easier
I'll talk about some real world use
cases for where I've used this before
and where I think it fits in really well
and in the end I'm going to show a real
world bug that we had because of these
conversion operators so buckle in it's
going to be a wild ride okay so first
and foremost what are they let's write
one so suppose we have a struct here it
could be a class or a struct called
orange what I can do is write the word
operator followed by any type I think of
such as a float and then have that
return a float like 5.5 at its core this
is what I'm talking about this is called
a conversion operator what it allows us
to do is convert this type into this
type very simple how does it work well
if I have an orange over here I can just
be like float f equals orange check that
out and so if I go ahead and log that
and I'll run this then you can see I
print out 5.5 which is the value I was
returning here another way to do this is
to also cast orange to a float so if I
do that as an example you can see I get
the same result as you would expect and
then finally if you if you had a
function that took in a Flo like this
for example then you can just call Print
Flo with your orange and there we go
this accepts a float as you can see but
because there is a conversion that
exists for orange to float then we can
just pass it in and pretend it's a float
for all intents and purposes it's like
we we could just say that it's a float
now why on Earth is this useful that
might be the first thing you ask based
on this example this nonsensical example
that I've shown here and that's okay
maybe you think like that because you're
a beginner programmer and if you are I
have the perfect thing for you
brilliant.org the sponsor of this video
which by the way you can get started
using for free brilliant.org is an
amazing website filled with lots and
lots of really high quality courses on
various stem topics they have some
excellent beginner computer science
courses that they've recently started
expanding they have this really good
visual engaging and interactive way of
teaching that applies to all of their
courses it's a really good way to learn
how to think like a programmer but then
with some of their new courses they've
actually been expanding this to include
writing actual code and building
programs in Python and this great way of
teaching also extends into all of their
math courses of which they have a lot
from The Everyday Math course that's
really really good for beginners all the
way up to Advanced topics such as
calculus but again presenting all of
this visually giving you these widgets
that you can play with quizzing you to
make sure that you're paying attention
and actually understanding what they're
teaching you and you don't have to take
my word for it cuz you can just try it
out yourself for free they have a 30-day
free trial that you can use to try out
everything on their platform just go to
brilliant.org Theo link will be in the
description below and if if you do go on
to like it brilliant have been nice
enough to offer 20% off an annual
membership using that link in the
description huge thank you to
brilliant.org as always for sponsoring
this video all right so back to
conversion operators how is this useful
let me show you some more real world use
cases of this so the first example I
have for you is one that is actually
present in the C++ library but we're
going to write it out ourselves and that
is a scoped pointer so a scoped pointer
it's a unique pointer in C++ I like to
call it a scope pointer just because it
makes sense that it's somewhat tied to a
scope this example I have here
doesn't actually fulfill its purpose
which technically is to delete pointer
in the destructor like this but anyway
suppose we have a scope pointer and
maybe let's give it something to wrap
such as this little entity struct so if
we have a scope pointer wrapping this
entity so we can set it equal to a new
entity for example if you have no idea
what a scope pointer is by the way then
I have a video All About smart pointers
check it out it'll be linked up there
this class basically just means that we
can automate the deletion of it because
you can see that when this stack object
goes out of scope it will call delete so
we don't have to manually free this
entity so a really common thing for us
to want to do just with regular pointers
like if this has just been a regular
entity pointer is to check to see if
it's null right and we can do that in
C++ in a couple ways the more
traditional way is probably just by
writing something like this so for
example if entity is not null pointer
this is by the way an exclanation markk
and an equal sign the LI is just making
it one but another even cleaner way that
we can write this is just like this and
the reason why this works is because of
a couple reasons potentially the
simplest explanation is just that a
pointer is an integer and a bullying is
also an integer for the same reason why
this would work and this would work for
null this also works because it's an
integer we also have the ability to
actually cast a pointer like this into a
bull if we wanted it to be of the Bull
type specifically and of course we can
also reverse this by checking to see if
it is null like that because if the
entity pointer is zero then that of
course is false and we will enter this
Branch so to tie this into a more of a
real world example if we had a function
over here called process entity and it
took in like an entity pointer then we
might want to do something like if not
entity return or if the entity is valid
let's do some kind of processing over
here now if we want to actually wrap
this in a scoped pointer and then pass
that in over here which in this case
you'd probably want to not copy the
object for obvious reasons cuz if it
gets destroyed it will delete the entity
then we lose the ability to do this
so we can call Process entity with e
let's get rid of all this that's what
our calling code looks like but then
we're not able to check this because
it's a scoped pointer it's not an actual
pointer anymore it's an instance of an
object that wraps our actual pointer
inside so what are our options with this
well we could add something to the class
something like is valid for example
which would just return You Know M
pointer doesn't equal null or M poter
cast to a bull whatever and then we
could just write some codes such as is
valid and that makes sense and that's
great and if you want to do that that's
more than fine but we can actually
retain the same functionality if we
wanted to by just using a conversion
operator because what if we could just
treat this scoped pointer as a bull and
of course we can we just need to write
in operator bull we'll make it const and
we will return M pointer doesn't equal
null pointer or if you want to keep both
functions you can always just return is
valid inside our scope pointer class and
now if we scroll down you can see that
this becomes valid and for me personally
I like the way this looks I think it
makes a lot of sense and it's actually
quite common like for example the C++
standard Library does this as well so if
I use a unique pointer instead of my
scoped pointer I'll just have to make
sure that it's an explicit Constructor
like this then you can see that this
works fine as well and that's because
unique pointer also contains an operator
buol it's got a conversion operator that
will return get does not equal null
pointer and get just retrieves the
underlying pointer so for this
particular case in my opinion it's
basically a no-brainer I don't see any
controversy with writing a bull
conversion operator I think it's great
now let's move on to another example
this one's a little bit more complicated
we have a timer it it's pretty simple
the way it works we call start we call
stop it starts a timer it stops the
timer and then we have a couple
functions to get the timer duration
either in seconds or in milliseconds so
the usage of this might be something
like timer timer timer do start when we
want to start it timer do stop when we
want to stop it and then finally timer
get millisecs or get seconds if we want
to retrieve the result of that timing
and then this timer. get seconds we
would typically assign into a double
like this now what we could do though
because the underlying way that we use
timers is it just contains a time which
in this case we're using as a double why
don't we just write an operator double
we could have a conversion operator into
a double to avoid having to call a
function and of course you can do that
so we can just write operator double
const return and then we have a choice
here get seconds or get milliseconds so
let's just say will return get seconds
so now we don't have to do this we can
just use timer as if it's a double we
can pass it into any function that might
want to accept a double and we can even
do math on it like it was a double so
for example I could have an additional
timer maybe timing some kind of other
operation and then if I wanted to get
the combined time of both of these I
could just add them together and it goes
into a double and everything's great and
it looks nice but here's the issue it is
a little bit harder to read now because
we have two different options we can
retrieve this in seconds we can retrieve
this in milliseconds this does not
specify what it is it's very easy for us
to accidentally use this as a double
thinking well surely it must be
returning milliseconds or surely it must
be returning seconds and it ends up
being the wrong thing so we're
introducing this kind of ambiguity
that's making this less functional or
less well functional I should say this
is exactly a scenario where if we had
just called get seconds even though yes
it is more code and it does look less
clean it provides more information and I
think that's one of the most important
things about programming you are using
the English language here to express
code in a way that's not just readable
to the computer not just understandable
by the compiler but also understandable
by humans presumably so typically you're
in a situation where more is more if
your code can provide more clarity you
should do that and it's definitely much
better to do that rather than try and be
cool for example and just use conversion
operators and then have to write
comments such as this is in seconds by
the way we don't want to do that that
that's bad the code should be
self-documenting in this case and that's
how we achieve that and now let's switch
over into Hazel and I'll show you some
real world examples of where this can go
wrong and go right so over here we have
this fun little function that just
displays the performance of certain
timers inside Hazel per frame so as the
game engine is running we have the
ability to time certain functions and we
can display the per frame timings live
in the UI and we had a bug where inside
this so this is supposed to show how
long all of these functions take we were
just seeing 0 milliseconds everywhere so
you can see as this is running we're
just seeing zeros well if we take a look
at the code this is the code that is
actually displaying all of this in our
UI using imuy you can see we're
iterating over this previous Frame data
and we're also using const Auto here for
the actual types inside this structured
binding we're then actually writing the
text in the UI using this so you can see
we're trying to use this as a float to
three decimal places and we're passing
in per Frame data as that first argument
over here so what is per Frame data I'll
check this out per Frame data is a
struct okay so we're trying to treat
that struct as a float I guess let's
take a look at what the struct is so
this is the struct it contains a float
time and it contains a un 32t samples so
this is the number of samples that it
gathered throughout the course of a
frame because these timers show the
cumulative time of that function across
the entire frame so if it's called 100
times it will contain the sum of all of
those individual timings and there is
that operator float the operator float
that returns time so in other words we
can just use per Frame data as a float
in which case we can completely ignore
this samples variable we don't care
about it we just want to use the per
Frame data struct as a float and that's
fine now normally that would work there
wouldn't really be an issue with that
but the issue here unfortunately is
ambiguity the thing is imuy text much
like print F just allows us to specify a
bunch of parameters in various types and
then since it has to accept parameters
in all of those various types it does so
if we take a look at how the function is
written it just takes in this list of
variable arguments of any type and
that's really where the problem is perf
Frame data can be per Frame data or it
can be a float so in this case it's just
like well I'm cool with it being that
original stru type there's no reason for
me to convert it into a float so
therefore I'll leave it at that original
type now this may have worked in the
past because it's possible that this per
Frame data which by the way I think was
called something like time before I
refactored this code on a live stream
whilst I was fixing this bug this could
have originally been a float itself it
might not have been that per Frame data
struct but then later on maybe we
decided to also store the sample count
the number of samples so now obviously
this had to become a struct it got
changed into a struct instead of just
being a a single float and whilst
writing this the author may have wanted
to keep this still compatible with the
existing code by allowing it to be cast
into a float to be converted into a
float using this conversion operator but
the problem is if you have a function
that accepts both then of course it's
going to use that original type if it
can get away with using that type
without doing any conversion that is of
course the first thing that it tries to
do so my point with this is that in this
case this causes ambiguity thanks to
that conversion operator if we hadn't
had the conversion operator then no one
would try and just passing that struct
they would have to calltime and per
frame data. time is very clear you're
showing the time and you're showing the
samples of course it doesn't make sense
to just pass in per Frame data because
what part of that data are you showing
but in the past as I mentioned it used
to be a float so there was no ambiguity
there was no samples it was just time
and that made perfect sense so in this
case even though we could also achieve
this working by simply casting it to a
float so if we try that instead because
now we're actually being like no no no I
want this to be treated as a float even
though though you can take in that other
struct I'm actually converting it myself
into a float in this case so you can see
in this case that everything's working
right we're not getting timings of zero
apart from some places where it might
make sense we're generally getting data
now so even though we could achieve this
by casting this to a float I would say
that the correct decision here would be
to Simply write time because that makes
the most sense to the human reading and
of course it works properly because time
itself is a float and finally let me
show you a recent real world example in
which I used these conversion operators
and I'm not so sure if I like the way
that I use them so recently I was
working on the asynchronous asset
loading system inside Hazel and so now
we have a couple new functions we have
asset manager get asset async this
allows us to asynchronously request an
asset by its handle if it hasn't loaded
we're not going to get it immediately
it's just going to cue the load on a
background thread but if we do have it
available to use the aset system will
serve us that asset and we can use it so
because of this added layer of
complexity meaning we we're not sure if
we're going to get the actual asset we
asked for or potentially a placeholder
and if we do get a placeholder we might
want to use it but we might just not
want to do the thing at all so if we get
a mesh placeholder let's just not render
the mesh this frame for example because
there are now all of these possibilities
instead of just getting a ref static
mesh back in this example as we would
have before if we synchronously
requested that asset we get an async
asset result and this async asset result
contains two things basically it
contains an asset and then just a bull a
little flag that's called is ready which
basically tells us whether or not we got
the asset we requested so basically this
asset is going to be one of two things
it's either going to be the real asset
that we asked for or it's going to be a
placeholder so in order for us to know
and respond accordingly we have a buling
just to just to tell us whether or not
this is the real one or the placeholder
but here's the thing as I have
introduced this new function get asset
async and I'm going through the code and
I'm changing it in places where it makes
sense to get things asynchronously to
get things asynchronously and as I'm
going through the code and I'm beginning
to use this function I'm realizing that
I want to use it in a couple different
ways sometimes I'm fine with the
placeholder I don't care in which case I
want to go through and I just want to
change get asset into get asset acing so
for example this is a completely random
place that I just found by searching
where we get the asset synchronously so
we're just calling get asset and it
gives us the texture that we've asked
for I want to be able to just change
this code to get asset async and in this
case look at that I don't have to change
the type at all because I know that this
is going to give me one of two things
either the actual texture I asked for if
it's loaded and ready for use or a
placeholder that I can use instead if I
had to go in and then change this to be
an async asset result and then when
using it I have to change this from
texture to texture. asset that's just I
don't like that at all that's just not
very clean and in this case I truly
don't care which one I get so it makes
sense for me to just keep using texture
but now suddenly I'm getting it
asynchronously which basically for the
calling code just means that I'm never
going to block the calling thread while
I load that asset but in other cases
like where we were before it doesn't
make sense to render like a placeholder
mesh I just maybe don't want to render
that mesh at all this Frame just skip it
render nothing until it's ready for
rendering in which case I'd have to come
back here and use this is ready bullying
to see whether or not that asset is
ready so I would choose to receive an
actual async asset result and then I'd
have to check to see if it's ready and
if it is ready then I can call Asset and
use it but here is where conversion
operators come in and make this a lot
cleaner cleaner but probably not
semantically more clear in fact the
opposite inside async asset result where
I have my asset and is ready I actually
have two different conversion operators
we've got one that will convert this
into ref of T this is templated by the
way since assets can obviously be a wide
variety of types and then an operator
bull that returns is ready which allows
us to use this as a bull so note that
I'm not returning asset which is a ref
but the ref class inside Hazel also has
these bull conversion operators in that
case it would just be checking to see if
the asset is null or not but the asset
is basically never going to be null it's
either going to be the placeholder or
the real asset so specifically here I'm
checking to see if it's ready I'm
returning is ready because if it's false
I got a placeholder if it's true I got
the real asset and so those two things
that I showed you is ready an asset we
actually need none of them because this
will call the operate a bull to check to
see if it's ready or not cuz we're using
it in the context of a bull in here and
then this will call this conversion
operator and give us our asset because
we're just using it as if it's an asset
and so to be honest like it's pretty
nice we get to not care whether or not
we treat it like an async asset result
or just like the real asset but if we do
choose to treat it like an async asset
result we can check to see if we got the
real asset we asked for and then just
use it accordingly but the problem with
this is that it's not immediately clear
what we're actually doing here are we
checking to see if the asset is at null
or not that's what it appears to me at
first glance whereas if I explicitly
used is ready that would technically
make more sense but you could argue that
with the variable name here static mesh
result you're obviously checking to see
if the result succeeded in a way because
it's in the name and if you read this if
static mesh result that kind of implies
whether or not the result was successful
whether or not it gave you the asset
that you wanted and then technically
speaking even though I'm explicitly
getting the mesh Source here and making
a new variable out of it this function
which takes in a mesh Source I could
just provide it with the mesh Source
result and of course it would still work
I'm just being a little bit more
explicit here because I find that that
helps the readability so yeah this is an
example where I'm on the fence I kind of
like it to be honest because it keeps
Everything clean but it's definitely got
a little bit of a learning curve and I
find that with C++
sometimes if you can avoid having a
learning curve for the way that you're
using the language and every developer
just understands it out of the box that
of course is a better place to be anyway
I hope you guys enjoyed this video if
you did please don't forget to hit the
like button what are your thoughts about
conversion operators do you use them do
you like them do you try and steer clear
of them do you hate them with a passion
let me know in the comments section
below and while you're down there let me
know what you think I should cover next
in the C++ series I'll see you guys next
time goodbye